When I arrived in Kiev,
عندما وصلت إلى كييف،
on February 1 this year,
في الأول من فبراير هذا العام،
Independence Square was under siege,
كان ميدان الاستقلال تحت الحصار
surrounded by police loyal to the government.
محاطاً بالشرطة الموالية للحكومة.
The protesters who occupied Maidan,
احتل المتظاهرون ميدان الاستقلال،
as the square is known,
ما تطلقون عليه اسم سكوير،
prepared for battle,
متجهزين للمعركة،
stockpiling homemade weapons
وبحوزتهم أسلحة منزلية الصنع
and mass-producing improvised body armor.
و بصدورهم العارية.
The Euromaidan protests began peacefully at the end of 2013,
بدأت مظاهرات الميدان الأوروبي بشكل سلمي في نهاية عام 2013،
after the president of Ukraine, Viktor Yanukovych,
بعد رفض الرئيس الأوكراني فيكتور ينكوفيتش
rejected a far-reaching accord with the European Union
اتفاقية طويلة الأمد مع الاتحاد الأوروبي
in favor of stronger ties with Russia.
لصالح علاقات أقوى مع روسيا.
In response, tens of thousands of dissatisfied citizens
وكردة فعل، قام عشرات الآلاف من المواطنين الغاضبين
poured into central Kiev to demonstrate against this allegiance.
بالتدفق إلى وسط كييف للتظاهر ضد هذا التحالف.
As the months passed,
وعلى مدار عدة شهور،
confrontations between police and civilians intensified.
اشتدت حدة المواجهات بين الشرطة والمدنيين.
I set up a makeshift portrait studio by the barricades on Hrushevsky Street.
قمت بإقامة معرض مؤقت للصور بالقرب من المتاريس على شارع غروفيشكي.
There, I photographed the fighters against a black curtain,
هناك قمت بتصوير المقاتلين ضد الحظر الأسود،
a curtain that obscured the highly seductive and visual backdrop
حظر حجب ستاراً مرئياً ومغرياً جداً
of fire, ice and smoke.
من النار والثلج والدخان.
In order to tell the individual human stories here,
وحتى أخبركم بقصص الأفراد من الناس هنا،
I felt that I needed to remove the dramatic visuals
شعرت بأن عليّ إزالة المظاهر الدرامية
that had become so familiar and repetitive within the mainstream media.
التي قد أصبحت مألوفة جداً ومتكررة على وسائل إعلام الرئيسية.
What I was witnessing was not only news, but also history.
لم يكن ما كنت أشهده أخباراً فحسب، إنه تاريخ أيضاً.
With this realization,
وبهذا الإدراك،
I was free from the photojournalistic conventions
كنت محررة من اتفاقيات التصوير الصحفي
of the newspaper and the magazine.
للجريدة أو المجلة.
Oleg, Vasiliy and Maxim were all ordinary men,
كان كلاً من أوليغ وفاسيلي وماكسيم رجالاً عاديين،
with ordinary lives from ordinary towns.
بحياة عادية أتوا من مدن عادية.
But the elaborate costumes that they had bedecked themselves in
لكن البزات المفصلة التي زينوا أنفسهم بها
were quite extraordinary.
كانت مميزة إلى حد ما.
I say the word "costume"
أقول كلمة "بزة"
because these were not clothes that had been issued
لأن هذه لم تكن ملابس قد صنعها
or coordinated by anyone.
أو نسقها أحد ما.
They were improvised uniforms
كانت أزياء إرتجالية
made up of decommissioned military equipment,
مصنوعة من معدات عسكرية لا تستعمل
irregular combat fatigues and trophies taken from the police.
وملابس عسكرية غير عادية ونصب تذكارية مأخوذة من الشرطة.
I became interested in the way they were choosing to represent themselves,
أصبحت مهتمة بالطريقة التي يختارونها لتقديم أنفسهم،
this outward expression of masculinity,
هذا التعبير الصريح عن الرجولة
the ideal of the warrior.
ومفهوم المقاتل.
I worked slowly, using an analog film camera
عملت ببطء مستخدمة آلة تصوير تماثلية
with a manual focusing loop and a handheld light meter.
ودليل استعمال لتركيز العدسة ومقياس ضوء جيبي.
The process is old-fashioned.
إن العملية على الطراز القديم.
It gives me time to speak with each person
إنها تعطيني الوقت للحديث مع كل شخص
and to look at them, in silence, while they look back at me.
والنظر إليهم، في صمت، بينما يبادلونني النظرات.
Rising tensions culminated in the worst day of violence
توجت التوترات المتزايدة في أسوء يوم للعنف
on February 20,
في العشرين من فبراير،
which became known as Bloody Thursday.
والذي أصبح معروفاً باسم الخميس الدامي.
Snipers, loyal to the government,
بدأ القناصة الموالون للحكومة
started firing on the civilians and protesters on Institutskaya Street.
ضرب النار على المدنيين والمتظاهرين على شارع إنستتيسكا.
Many were killed in a very short space of time.
قتل العديد من الأشخاص خلال وقت قصير جداً.
The reception of the Hotel Ukraine became a makeshift morgue.
أصبحت قاعة استقبال فندق أوكرانيا مشرحة مؤقتة.
There were lines of bodies laid in the street.
كانت هناك صفوف من الجثث ملقاة في الشارع.
And there was blood all over the pavements.
وكان هناك دم في أرجاء الممرات.
The following day, President Yanukovych fled Ukraine.
وفي اليوم التالي، هرب الرئيس ينكوفيتش من أوكرانيا.
In all, three months of protests
وبالمجمل، ثلاثة شهور من المظاهرات
resulted in more than 120 confirmed dead
راح ضحيتها أكثر من 120 من القتلى المؤكدين
and many more missing.
والكثير الكثير من المفقودين.
History unfolded quickly,
انجلى التاريخ وبسرعة،
but celebration remained elusive in Maidan.
ولكن الاحتفال بقي أمراً تم تجنبه في الميدان.
As the days passed in Kiev's central square,
وبمرور الأيام في الساحة المركزية لكييف،
streams of armed fighters
مجموعات من المقاتلين المسلحين
were joined by tens of thousands of ordinary people,
وبمشاركة عشرات الآلاف من الناس العاديين
filling the streets in an act of collective mourning.
يملئون الشوارع في حداد جماعي.
Many were women who often carried flowers
العديد كانوا من النساء اللواتي غالباً ما حملن الورود
that they had brought to lay as marks of respect for the dead.
التي جلبنها لوضعها كإشارات احترام للموتى.
They came day after day
أتين يوماً بعد يوم
Sadness enveloped Maidan.
غشى الحزن الميدان.
It was quiet and I could hear the birds singing.
كان هادئاً وكنت أستطيع سماع تغريد الطيور.
I hadn't heard that before.
لم أكن أسمعه من قبل.
I stopped women as they approached the barricades
أوقفت النساء عندما اقتربن من المتاريس
to lay their tributes
لوضع الأكاليل
and asked to make their picture.
وطلبت منهم التقاط صورة لهن.
Most women cried when I photographed them.
معظم النساء بكين عندما قمت بتصويرهن.
On the first day, my fixer, Emine, and I cried
في اليوم الأول، بكيت أنا ومساعدتي إيمان
with almost every woman who visited our studio.
مع تقريباً كل النساء اللاتي زرن الأستوديو خاصتنا.
There had been such a noticeable absence of women
لقد كان هناك نوع من الغياب الملحوظ للنساء
up until that point.
حتى هذه اللحظة.
And the color of their pastel coats,
ولون معاطفهن الباهتة
their shiny handbags,
وحقائبهن اللامعة
and the bunches of red carnations,
وباقات القرنفل الأحمر
white tulips and yellow roses that they carried
والتيوليب الأبيض والورود الصفراء اللاتي حملنها
jarred with the blackened square
تضيق مع الميدان سيء السمعة
and the blackened men who were encamped there.
والرجال سيئي السمعة الذين خيموا هناك.
It is clear to me that these two sets of pictures
من الواضح بالنسبة لي أن تلك المجموعتان من الصور
don't make much sense without the other.
لا تفهما دون بعضهما.
They are about men and women and the way we are --
هي عن رجال ونساء والطريقة التي نحن عليها--
not the way we look, but the way we are.
ليست الطريقة التي نظهر بها، لكن الطريقة التي نحن عليها.
They speak about different gender roles in conflict,
إنها صور تتحدث عن اختلاف أدوار النوع الاجتماعي في النزاع،
not only in Maidan, and not only in Ukraine.
ليس في الميدان فحسب وليس في أوكرانيا وحدها.
Men fight most wars and women mourn them.
يقاتل الرجال في أغلب الحروب وتشيعهم النساء.
If the men showed the ideal of the warrior,
إذا أظهر الرجال مفهوم المقاتل،
then the women showed the implications of such violence.
فإن النساء أظهرن تأثيرات مثل هذا العنف.
When I made these pictures,
عندما قمت بالتقاط هذه الصور،
I believed that I was documenting the end of violent events in Ukraine.
اعتقدت أنني أوثق نهاية أحداث العنف في أوكرانيا.
But now I understand that it is a record of the beginning.
ولكنني الآن أفهم أنه تسجيل للبداية.
Today, the death toll stands around 3,000,
اليوم، يقف عداد القتلى على حوالي 3000
while hundreds of thousands have been displaced.
بينما قد تم ترحيل مئات الآلاف.
I was in Ukraine again six weeks ago.
كنت في أوكرانيا مرة أخرى قبل ستة أسابيع.
In Maidan, the barricades have been dismantled,
تم حل المتاريس في الميدان
and the paving stones which were used as weapons during the protests replaced,
وتم استبدال بلاط الممرات الذي استعمل كسلاح خلال المظاهرات،
so that traffic flows freely through the center of the square.
إذن فحركة المرور تتدفق بحرية وسط الميدان.
The fighters, the women and the flowers are gone.
ذهب المقاتلون والنساء وذهبت الأزهار.
A huge billboard depicting geese flying over a wheat field
تحلق لوحة إعلانات ضخمة تصور المسيح يطير فوق حقل قمح
covers the burned-out shell of the trade union's building
تغطي قبة مبنى اتحاد التجارة المحترق
and proclaims,
وتعلن،
"Glory to Ukraine.
"المجد لأوكرانيا.
Glory to heroes."
المجد للأبطال."
Thank you.
شكراً لكم.
(Applause).
(تصفيق).